Are you thinking about moving to central
Texas and wondering if Temple, Texas
could be right for you? Then you'll
definitely want to watch this video.
Today we are diving into a full map tour
of Temple, Texas, including employers,
dining, schools, neighborhoods,
shopping, and just why this area
continues to grow like crazy. So whether
you are relocating for work lifestyle or
just want that central Texas charm
without the Austin price tag, you'll
definitely want to watch this video.
Don't forget to like, subscribe, and
click the bell icon so that you can stay
uptodate on all things real estate here
in Central Texas.
[Music]
And before we dive into our full map
tour, I want to let you know about
something really, really helpful,
especially if you're in research mode.
So, if you head on over to
livinginanc.com
and you head to the explore the area
tab,
we have some really amazing resources
for people relocating here and a feature
that really people keep thanking us for.
So, we built in an interactive map of
Temple, Texas and all the surrounding
areas. You can click on any suburb or
city if you're considering and instantly
access videos and breakdowns of each
area. So, here we have Temple, Texas. It
pops up the area and then you can say,
"Huh, well, what's going on here in
Belton or Little River Academy, Troy,
Morgan's Point. There's a lot of
overlap, especially between Temple and
Belton, but this will give you a really
good idea of where everything is and let
you play around a little bit. And if
you're planning to buy a home here, you
can head on over to the buy tab,
fill out a quick form, and we'll set up
a one-on-one call with you to walk
through the map um in more detail based
on your timeline, budget, and wish list.
We're getting a ton of these filled out
every week, and people are loving how
much clarity this brings. So, please pop
on over to the site and explore. Um I
think there's a lot of really helpful
information for you there. Okay, so
let's talk a little bit about Temple,
Texas. Okay, so this is just an overall
map view. We're going to zoom out quite
a bit here and just look at the
beautiful state of Texas. And as we zoom
in, you have Austin down here,
Dallas for Worth here, Waco here, and
then this is that I35 corridor that goes
all the way down. and Temple is right
here in between Waco and Austin. If you
are considering Temple, you probably
want to head over and watch the map tour
of Belton, Texas because again, there's
just so much overlap and you might pick
up something from there that wasn't
discussed here. Just keep you a little
bit um overly informed or extra
informed. So, in terms of beaches, we
have Galveastston, Corpus Christi, and
then a little bit more south, you have
South South Padre Island. I spent a lot
of time there growing up, but you are
probably 4 to 6 hours away from a major
beach if you want that. And if you move
to Temple, Texas, you're only an hour
north of Austin, Texas. um about 40 35
to 40 minutes south of Waco, Texas and
20 to 25 minutes east of Fort Cavazos.
So location is fantastic. Let's zoom in
and take a look at Temple. As you can
see here, Austin, Texas,
and then above Austin, you'll see some
other really popular areas. Round Rock,
um, Cedar Park,
Georgetown, those are growing like
crazy. And then Gerald as we get closer
to us. And then So, I just did a really
cool uh tour of Celo, Texas. It's the
cutest little gem. Lots of golf course
living. Um, just kind of upscale area.
If you want to check out So, Texas more
in detail, you can find that video on my
site.
But as we zoom in,
we have Temple, Texas outlined in red
here. It is part of
Bell County. In terms of population,
Temple's population is now just over
92,000
and it continues to grow, uh, climbing
year-over-year. This area is
experiencing tremendous growth thanks to
a booming healthc care industry,
affordable cost of living, and a sweet
spot location between major Texas meros.
People are relocating here from across
the state, country just for opportunity,
lifestyle, and community. I did it
myself. I'm from Las Vegas and I love
it. I wouldn't change a thing. You'll
also note again that Temple runs or the
I35 rather runs smack through Temple.
Again, we have Celo here, Belton, Little
River Academy, Troy, Nolanville, and as
you head more west, Harker Heights,
Colleen, Fort Kavazos. Um, one of my
favorite spots that I'm um a little
partial to, Morgan's Point Resort near
the lake. I think it's beautiful deer
roaming your neighborhood. But just
being right on this I35 corridor makes
this a major major hot spot. We So
Temple is a regional employment hub,
especially for healthcare and
distribution. Um that that is something
that I feel is just so missed and not
incredibly known about this area. We
have Baylor Scott and White Medical
Center, MLAN Children's Hospital, the VA
Medical Center, MLAN Company, which is
national distribution, Wilson Art
Manufacturing, and SpaceX in McGregor.
So, some of my SpaceX people are
actually purchasing in Troy, Moody, and
North Temple. And then of course, don't
forget we have Fort Cavazos, formerly
Fort Hood, which is just west, bringing
military
uh connected families and job stability
to this area. You can find Fort Kavazos
right here.
So, just west on the 14 on I-14,
here's 35. And again, 35 runs through.
317 is the main street basically through
Belton. Um, West Adams kind of
intersects through there and then
14 out to Fort Kavazos
and then 35 through Temple
and part of Belton down here.
So, if you're thinking about moving to
the Temple area, definitely explore some
of these other areas. That's where that
map tour is going to be extra helpful.
Okay, so let's talk about some key
neighborhoods. I'm going to hop on over
to the MLS just so you can see from a
realtor's perspective if I were to help
you find a home what we would be looking
at. So, if I type in Temple, Texas and
active homes, there are 740 matches
right now. And then if I do just new
construction, so let's just say 2024 and
newer, you have 229 homes listed. That
doesn't mean that there's not more
inventory. A lot of these builders keep
um inventory records which I can help
get for you um and they don't always
list them into MLS right away. They wait
till certain stages and whatnot. But
just in the MLS, our multiple listing
service, that is how many active homes
we have. If I take out the newer homes
and we just look at homes in Temple and
we look at this little map search,
this is everything technically within
Temple.
Now, if I were to set you up on a
search, I would probably discuss what
your motivation is because you'd likely
want to consider Belton as well. And
then if you decide on Belin
alternatively, um I'll ask you why is
that? Because if you want Belton ISD, if
that's particularly what you're looking
for, a lot of Temple falls in Belton ISD
and part of Temple also falls in Academy
ISD. So all very important pieces that
we would go over or things that you
should consider. So in terms of area,
there's so so much happening here. Um,
one of the fastest growing areas is
going to be West Temple, which is zoned
Belton ISD, close to Lake Belton.
So, this is Lake Belton. This is West
Adams,
which is basically the main street
through Temple and into
Belton.
There are a lot of homes over here
and a lot of newer developments. So, we
have Hills of Westwood, the Parks at
Westfield. Um, we have Hills of Westwood
kind of in this area, Parks of
Westfield's kind of in this area.
Wildflower Country Club, if you want
golf course living, is right here. And
then Mesa Ridge has a lot of new
construction as well. It's going to be,
let's see, we've got 317 in Adams, so
it's like in this area.
We have uh the groves at Lakewood Ranch,
but variety of price points ranging from
300,000 all the way up to a million, you
know, just kind of depending on what
you're looking for. West Adams right
here,
West Temple. This is growing immensely
again because of Belistd, also because
of being close to the lake. But being
right off of West Adams, you have all
well, not all, but you have a lot of
really great shopping, dining, and
amenities right there. So, I'd say kind
of in
just all along West Adams, you have a
tons of dining and shopping in these
areas in this area, the Soul Garden,
Lariv, um, Three West, and then you have
Starbucks,
all of your fast food chains,
Walmart. You have a Walmart right there.
But a lot of things, and also boutique
shops here on West Adams. So, a lot of
people like to be really close to there.
And then if we go into temple a little
bit deeper, right in
this area off of 363.
So again, this is West Adams, right?
West Temple. You have
the loop 363 here and you have 35. Well,
right here is a ton of shopping. You
have Home Depot, Target, Best Buy. You
have like Specs, Liquor, Pet Stores,
restaurants like BJ's, Chipotle,
those sort of things in that spot. Olive
Garden. Other big area of shopping
is right here off of 190. You have Hobby
Lobby,
um, Ulta, Marshalls,
Chew Carnival, Chase Bank, Freezing
Point Crearyy. Such good ice cream. If
you've ever had Cold Stone, it's similar
to that. In addition to shopping, if you
come off of
31st Street, which is the major
street through Temple, kind of going
north and south, right off of uh the
190, you have right over here, you have
HB,
bunch of little restaurants kind of
tucked away in there, fast food,
Starbucks,
You have MLAN Children's Hospital. And
then if you stay on 31st Street, you
also have a Sam's Club down in here,
another Walmart. So I'd say 31st and
Adams are really popular just in terms
of proximity to shopping, but really
you're not very far from anything no
matter where you go. So, when we talk
about being a major medical hub, right
off of 31st Street, you have Baylor
Scott and White Main Medical Facility.
And then over here, which I don't know
why that's not really popping up, is
MLAN Children's Hospital. Those are
huge. And then you also have the VA
hospital. So again, just in in terms of
where you're looking to be, whether
you're a resident, whether you're just
looking to be closer to the hospital,
whether you're a veteran looking to be
close to the VA hospital, um you know,
South Temple over here might be really
desirable for you. I also did a video on
homes or neighborhoods near the
hospitals in Temple. And then downtown
Temple, you have the Temple Railroad and
Heritage Museum. Old Jod's Restaurant
right here is a popular one.
Oh my gosh, Trina's Trina's Pizza and
Tap Room is fantastic. They'll also do
birthday parties there if you if you
decide to do that. But downtown is
really really
it's kind of in this areaish. Downtown
is really, really, really developing.
Um, there's also local shops, murals.
Bird Creek Burgers has the best burgers
ever. They have really awesome garlic
parmesan fries. Uh there's also PNET
Italian Dining. We'll go there a lot for
date night. It's uh there's also Cheese,
which is a more expensive steakhouse. Um
we we kind of lean more towards
Picnettis just because we like the food
probably better, but it's less
expensive. Also, um and yeah, there's
just so much more happening down there.
If you're thinking trying to decide
which neighborhood you or areas you're
looking to be in, now that we've kind of
discussed that, this is back to our map
search of available homes in Temple. You
can see there's a lot of homes really
everywhere. If you are looking to be
closer to the hospitals
and more South Temple,
there are a lot of communities off of
31st Street.
So, you have pockets of more established
communities
kind of tucked away behind the
hospitals, behind the shopping. Those
are some of more, like I said, your more
established communities. Um and then
over here you have more of like a mix of
new construction and established. But
then as you come down 31st Street,
you have um like you have Bellerra which
has some resale happening and a lot of
new construction. Kather's builds in
there, Eagle Ridge. So Bellaterara is a
big one. Um at the end of 31st Street by
Taylor's Valley, you also have Valley
Ranch. You have Balor Estates. Valor
Estates. They're still building some in
there. Okay, so farm to market this way.
FM93.
You have some communities up here. Um
some good variety of luxury and um just
like more affordable starter or
retirement homes. You have Frier's Bend,
Hartrick Crossing, and Hartrick Ranch.
Some of those builders are going to be
um some of your, you know, more custom
builders, but it's also some of your
production builders. Style um
Stylecraft, Kila, Omega, Flint Rock, I
think is in there. So, really great
options if you're thinking South Temple
and there's some overlap in Academy ISD.
If you are looking to be maybe closer to
the lake, um, closer to West Adams, you
want to fall more in Belton ISD, you
might really consider over here off West
Adams, off of 317. Really great driving
or very easy access because of its
because of it being off of 317. Again,
we have like Mesa Ridge, some of those
newer communities there, Morgan's Point.
There's some resale, Hills of Westwood.
There's a bunch of new homes kind of
right here off of West Adams, east of
363, but as you can see, there is a
surplus of options. School districts.
So, Temple ISD, you have Temple High
School, uh, growing elementary and
middle school options. You also nearby
you'll also find Belton ISD which is
zone for West Temple residents, Academy
ISD for some of those South Temple
people, Temple College, Texas&M Health
Science Center and medical training
programs. Uh private school options
including Holy Trinity Catholic High
School, Trinity Christian Schools, and
of course I can always um send you the
link for Temple ISD and Builton ISD if
you'd like to look a little bit more
there. Other dining favorites while I'm
on that topic, you have Meg's Cafe in
Temple. It's going to be off of 31st
Street.
Farm Fresh. They do a lot of local
sourcing. Bird Creek, I mentioned, Lar
Kitchen and Bar off of West Adams.
Miller Smokehouse. Nami is a bachi
style.
And then for local coffee spots, we have
Summer Moon off West Adams, a 1914
Coffee House, and Fire Street Roers. So,
in terms of growth and development, we
have downtown revitalization with art,
dining, and community events. Uh, the
West Adams corridor, which I've touched
on a lot, is seeing major growth in
housing and retail. The city is really
investing in infrastructure and parks as
the population just continues to grow.
Um, and then of course also being part
of that I 35 corridor, attracting tech,
healthcare, and logistical businesses.
We have um
outdoor and lifestyle. Oh my gosh, I was
sounds so silly, but being from Las
Vegas, I saw a lot of desert and cactus.
So, when I moved here, what was that 9
years ago, I was really shocked by just
how beautiful and how much there was to
do outdoors here. And so, you have
Belton Lake, so tons of lake, fishing,
boating, um paddle boarding,
kaying, whatever you want to do there.
And then uh like lots of times I'll go
on to I'll go to Deadfish Grill, have a
nice margarita overlooking Blue Lake.
It's just super beautiful. Morgan's
Point I touch on a lot saying it has
deer roaming the neighborhood. Uh tons
of trees and oak trees in those areas.
And a lot of the areas you go to, you'll
find more established neighborhoods with
those big trees. You can also find a lot
larger lots. So, you can really get a
lot more space and privacy in this price
point up here opposed to maybe the
Austin area, but you're not far. I mean,
an hour drive to get to, you know,
Austin. It took me an hour and 20
minutes to get to the airport uh to the
Austin airport the other day. You would
fly out of either Austin or Dallas. But
there's also tons of hiking trails. You
have uh Miller Springs Park, Pepper
Creek Trail, Whistle Stop Park, tons of
splash paths, multiple dog parks,
playgrounds, Lions Junction Family Water
Park, we have summer fun water park,
just a lot of really great things to
consider if you are looking into the
central Texas area. So whether you are
looking for a fresh start, a slower
pace, or a growing city with job
opportunity, Temple, Texas might be the
perfect move. And don't forget living in
ctx.com. Check out that interactive map
and also head on over to the buy or sell
pages if you're looking to buy or sell
and fill out those forms. I'd love to
speak with you. Um if you're not quite
ready to make a move, you can also
download my free relocation guide. Drop
your questions in the comments.
Subscribe for more tours and local
information. And reach out if you are
ready. I'm happy to help. Till next
time.